[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine online at computer.org software
welcome to software engineering radio
i'm your host akshay manchale today's
topic is data governance and i have two
guests with me jesse ashdown and uri
gillard jesse is a senior user
experience researcher at google
she led data governance research for
google cloud for three and a half years
before moving to leading privacy
security and trust research on google
wallet before google jesse led
enterprise research for t-mobile uri is
a group product manager at google for
the last four years helping cloud
customers achieve better governance of
their data through advanced policy
management and data organization tooling
prior to google ured held executive
product positions in security and cloud
companies such as forescout checkpoint
and various other startups
jesse and uri are both authors of the
o'reilly book data governance the
definitive guide jessie uri welcome to
the show thank you for having us to
start off maybe jesse can we start with
you can you define what data governance
is and why is it important
yeah definitely so i think one of the
things when
defining data governance is
really looking at it as a big picture
definition so often times when i talk to
people about data governance they're
like isn't that just data security and
it's not it's so much more than that it
is data security but it's also
organizing your data managing your data
how you are able to distribute your data
so that folks can use it and in that
same vein if we ask why is it important
who is it important for not to be
dramatic but it's wildly important
you know because how you're organizing
and managing your data is really how
you're able to leverage the data that
you have and definitely i mean this is
what we're going to talk pretty much the
entire session about is how you're
thinking about the data that you have
and how governance really kind of gets
you to a place of where you're able to
leverage that data and really utilize it
and so when we're thinking in that vein
who is it for it's really for everyone
all the way from
you know satisfying legal inside your
company to the
you know end customers somewhere right
who is exercising their right to delete
their data outside of these legal and
regulatory requirements that might say
you need to have these governance
policies are there other consequences of
not having any sort of governance
policies over the data that you have and
is it different for small companies
versus large companies in an unregulated
industry
yeah yes uh davao so obviously the
immediate go-to for people is like if i
don't have data governance legal or the
regulator will be after me but it's
really like putting legal and regulation
aside
data governance for example is about
understanding your data
if you have no understanding of your
data then you won't be able to
effectively use it you will not be able
to trust your data you will not be able
to efficiently manage the storage for
your data because you will creating
duplicates people will spending a lot of
their time hunting down tribal knowledge
oh i know this engineer who created this
data set that he will tell you what this
column means this kind of things so data
governance is really
part of the fabric of the data you use
in your organization and it's big or
small it's more about the size of your
data store rather than the size of your
organization
and
think about the fabric which has loose
threads which are beginning to fray
that is data fabric without governance
sometimes when i hear data governance i
think about maybe there are restrictions
on it maybe there are controls about how
you can access it etc
does that come at odds with actually
making use of that data for instance if
i'm a machine learning
engineer or a data scientist maybe i
want all access to everything that is
so that i can actually make the best
possible model for the problem that
we're solving so is it at odds with such
use cases or can they coexist in a way
you can balance the needs
so
the short answer is of course it depends
and the longer answer will be
data governance is more of an enabler in
my opinion than restrictor data
governance does not block you from data
it sort of like funnels you to the right
kind of data to use
to the for example the data with the
highest quality the data that is most
relevant
use
curated customer cases rather than raw
customer cases for examples
and when people think about data
governance
as data restriction tool the question to
be asked is like what exactly is it
restricting is it restricting access
okay why
and if the access is restricted because
the data is sensitive for example the
data should not be shared around the
organization so there's two immediate
follow-up questions one is
if the data is to be used only within
the organization and you are generating
a general purpose customer facing for
example machine learning model then
maybe you shouldn't because that
has issues with it or maybe if you
really want to do that go and formally
ask for that access because maybe the
organization needs to just record the
fact that you asked for it again data
governance is not a gate
to be you know unlocked or left over or
whatever it's more of a highway that you
need to properly signal and get on i
would add to that and this is definitely
what we're going to get more into of
data governance really being an enabler
and a lot of it which hopefully folks
will get out of listening to this is
a lot of it is how you think about it
and how you strategize you know and as
uri was saying if you're kind of
strategizing from that defensive
standpoint versus kind of offensive of
okay how do we you know protect the
things that we need to
but how do we democratize it at the same
time they don't have to be at odds but
it does take some thought and planning
and consideration in order for you to
get to that point
sounds great and
you mentioned earlier about
having a way to find and know what data
you have in your organization so how do
you go about classifying your data what
purpose does it serve do you have any
examples to talk about how data is
classified nicely versus something that
is not classified nicely
yeah it's a great question and one of
like my my favorite quotes with data
governance is you can't govern what you
don't know and that really
kind of stems back to your question of
you know about classification and
classification is really a place to
start you can't govern and govern
meaning like i can't restrict access i
can't you know kind of figure out what
sort of analytics even that i want to do
unless i really think about classifying
and i think sometimes when folks hear
classification they're like oh my gosh
i'm going to have to have 80 million
different
you know classes of my data and it's
going to take an inordinate amount of
tagging and things like that and it
could there's certainly companies that
do that but to your point of some
examples through the research that i've
done over years there's been many
different approaches that companies have
taken all the way from just a like
literal binary of red green right like
red data goes here and people don't use
it and green data goes here and people
use it to things that are kind of more
complex of like okay let's have our top
35 you know classes of data or
categories so we're going to have
marketing we're going to have financial
there's hr or what have you right and
then we're just going to look at these
you know 35 classes and categories and
that's what we're going to divide by and
then set policies on that i know i'm
jumping ahead a little bit by talking
about policies we'll get more to that
later but yeah kind of thinking about
classification it's a method of
organization
like uri i think you have to add to that
too
think about data classification as the
augmented reality glasses
that enable you to look at your data
and the underlying theme in the industry
generally today it's a combination of
manual label which jesse mentioned like
we have x categories and we need to like
manually curate them
and machine assisted
or even machine generated classification
like for example red green
red is everything we don't want to touch
maybe red data this data source always
produces red data you don't need a human
to do anything there you just mark this
data source as unsuitable or sensitive
and you're done
obviously classification and cataloging
has evolved beyond that
there is a lot of technical metadata
which is already available with your
data which is already immediately useful
to end users without even going through
actual classification
where did the data come from what is the
data source what is the data's lineage
like which data sources will use in
order to generate this data if you think
about structured data what is the table
name the column name those are useful
things that are already there if it's
unstructured data what is the file name
and then you can begin and this is where
we can talk a little bit about common
data classifications methods really
this is where you can begin and
going one layer deeper so one layer
deeper is
in image it's classic there's a lot of
data classification technologies for
image what it contains and there's a lot
of companies there also for structured
data it's a table it has columns you can
sample enough values from a column to
get a sense of what that column is it's
a nine digit number great
is it a nine digit social security
number or is it a nine digit phone
number there's patterns in the data that
can help you find that addresses names
gps coordinates ip addresses all of
those are like machine
capable
values that can be also detected and
extracted by machines
and now
you begin to lay over that with human
curation which is where we get that
overwhelming label that jesse mentioned
and you can say okay humans please tell
me if this is a customer email or an
employee email that is probably an
immediate thing a human can do and we
are seeing tools that allow people to
actually crowdfund this kind of
information and jesse i think you have
more about that yeah i'm so glad that
you brought that up you know i have a
funny story of a company that i had
interviewed and they were talking about
the curation of their data right
and sometimes these folks are called you
know data stewards or they're doing data
stewardship tasks and they're the person
who goes in and kind of as uri is saying
like that human
of okay is this you know an email
address is this you know kind of what is
this sort of thing
and this company had a full-time person
doing this job and that person
quit
and i quote because it was soul-sucking
you know and i think it's really you
know uri's point is so good about you
know the classification and curation is
so important but my goodness
having a person do all that no one's
gonna do it right and oftentimes it
doesn't get done at all because it's
nobody's full-time job and the poor
folks who it is you know i mean this is
just one case study right but you know
quit because they don't want to do that
so
you know there's many methods that the
answer isn't to just throw up your hands
and say i'm not going to classify
anything or we have to classify
everything but as uri is really getting
at finding those places can we leverage
you know some of that machine learning
or some of the technologies that have
come out that really automate some of
these things and then having you know
your kind of manual humans to do some of
these other things that the machines
can't quite do yet
i really like your initial
approach of just classifying it as red
and blue that takes you from having
absolutely no classification to some
sort of classification and that's really
nice however when you come to say a
large company you might end up seeing
data that's in different storage mediums
right like you might have a data lake
that's a dump all ground for things you
might have the database that's running
your operations you might have like logs
and metrics that is just operational
data can you talk a little bit about how
you
catalog these different data source in
different storage mediums so so this is
a bit where we talk about tooling and
what tools are available because you are
already saying there's a data store that
looks like this and another data store
that looks like that
and here's what not to do because i've
seen this done many times
when
you have this conversation with a vendor
and i'm very much aware that google
cloud is a vendor and the vendor says oh
that's easy first of all move all of
your data to this
new magical data store and everything
will be right with the world i have seen
many organizations who have a series of
graveyards where oh this vendor told us
to move there we started a sixth year
project
we moved half the data we still had to
use the data store that we originally
were migrating up for out of so we ended
up with two data stores and then another
vendor came and told us to move to a
third data store so now we have three
data stores and those seems to be
continuously duplicating so don't do
that
here's a better approach there's a lot
of third-party as well as first party in
which i mean like
provider based catalogs
all of these products have plugins and
integrations to all of the common data
stores again the
features and bells and whistles on each
of those plugins and each of those
categories differ
and this is where maybe you need to do a
sort of like ranked choice but at the
end of the day the industry is in a
place where
you can point a data catalog at a
certain data store it will scrape it it
will collect the technical metadata and
then you can decide what you want to
move what you want to further annotate
what you are satisfied with oh all of
this is green all of this is red and
move on think about a layered strategy
and also like land and expand strategy
is that like a plug-and-play sort of a
solution that you say might exist like
as a third-party tool or maybe even in
cloud providers where you can just point
to it and maybe does the machine
learning saying hey okay this looks like
a nine digit number so maybe this is
social security something so maybe i'm
gonna just limit access to this is there
an automated way to go from zero to
something when you're using third party
tools or cloud providers so
i want to break up break down this
question a little bit does cataloging
does classification
those are normally two different steps a
cataloging usually collects technical
metadata file names table names column
names
classification usually gets geared up by
please look at this table data set
like file bucket
and
classify the contents of this
destination
and the different classification tools
i'm obviously called as coming from
google cloud we have google cloud dlp
which is fairly robust actually was used
internally within google to sift through
some of our own data
interestingly enough we had a case where
google was doing some of its support for
some of its product over uh sort of like
chat interface
and that chat interface for regulatory
purposes
for regulatory reasons was captured
installed and customers would begin a
chat like hi i am so and so this is my
credit card number
please extend this subscription from
this value to that value
and that's a problem because that data
store speaking about governance was not
built to hold credit card numbers
despite that customers will really
insist about providing them
and one of the key initial uses for the
data classifier is find critical numbers
and actually eliminate them actually
delete them from the record because we
didn't want to keep them
so is this whole process easier in the
cloud that's an excellent question and
the topic of cloud is really relevant
when you talk about data classification
data cataloging because
think about the era that existed before
cloud there was your big data data
storage was a sql server on a mini tower
in some cubic and it will churn happily
its disk space and when you
needed to
get more data somebody needed to watch
over to the computer store and buy
another disk
or whatever
in the cloud there's an interesting
situation where suddenly your
infrastructure is unlimited
really your infrastructure is unlimited
costs are always going down and now you
are in a reverse situation where before
you had to censor yourself
in order not to overwhelm that poor sql
server in a mini tower in the cubic and
suddenly you are in a different
situation where like your default is
i'll just keep it in the cloud it will
be fine
and then enters the topic of data
governance and easier in the cloud it's
easier because compute is also more
accessible the data is immediately
reachable you don't need to plug in
another network connection to the sql
server you just access the data through
api
you have highly trained machine learning
models that can operate on your data and
classify it so from that aspect it is
here on the other side from the topics
of scale and volume it's actually harder
because people default to just ah let's
just throw it maybe we'll use it later
which kind of thing presents an
interesting governance challenge yes
that's exactly what i was going to
mention too is you know
sort of with the advent of cloud storage
as uri was saying you can just oh it's
you know i can store everything and just
dump and dump and dump and i think a lot
of
past dumpage is where we're seeing a lot
of the problems come now right because
people just thought well i'll just
collect everything and put it somewhere
and maybe now i'll put it in the cloud
because maybe that's cheaper than my
on-prem that can't hold it anymore right
but now you've got a governance
conundrum right you have
so much that honestly some of it might
not even be useful
that now you're having to sift through
and govern and this poor guy let's call
him joe is going to quit because he
doesn't want to curate all that right
so you know i think one of the takeaways
there
is there are tools that can help you but
also being strategic about what do you
save and really thinking about and i
guess we were kind of getting to that
with sort of our classification and you
know curation of
not that you have to then cut everything
that you don't need but just think about
it and consider because there might be
things that you put in this kind of
storage or that place you know folks
have different you know zones and data
lakes and what have you
but yeah don't store everything but
don't not store everything either
yeah i guess the elasticity of the cloud
definitely brings in more challenges of
course it makes certain things easier
but it does make things challenging uri
do you have something to add there
yeah so here's another unexpected
benefit of cloud which is formats
we jesse and i talked recently to a
government entity and that government
entity is actually bound by law to index
and archive all kinds of data
and it was funny they were sharing
anecdotally with you oh we are just
about to end
scanning the mountain of papers dating
back to the 1950s
and now we are finally getting into
advanced file formats such as microsoft
word six which is by the way the
microsoft word with those prevalent at
and
they were like those are available on
floppy disks and kind of stuff like that
now i'm not saying
cloud will magically solve all your
format problems but you can definitely
keep up with formats when all of your
data is accessible through the same
interface rather than a filing cabinet
which is another kind of on-prem in a
world where maybe they are dealing with
current data and they have an
application out there they have some
sort of like need or they understand the
importance of data governance
you're ingesting data so how do you
add policies around ingestion like what
is acceptable to store
do you have any comments about how to
think about that how to approach that
problem maybe jesse
yeah i mean i think again this sort of
goes to that idea of really being
planful of thinking about you know kind
of what you need to store and
you know one of the things so when we
talked about classification of you know
kind of these different ideas of you
know red green or kind of these top
things
uri and i in talking to many companies
have also heard different methods for
ingestion
so i certainly think that this isn't
something that there's only one good way
to do it so we've kind of heard
different ways of okay i'm going to
ingest everything into one place as like
a holding place and then once i curate
that data and i classify that data then
i will move it into another location
where i apply blanket policies
so in this location the policy is
everyone get access or the policy is no
one gets access or just these people do
so there's definitely a way to think
about it of you know different kind of
ingestion methods that you have
but the other thing too is is kind of
thinking about
what those policies are and how they
help you or how they hinder you and this
is something that we've heard a lot of
companies talk about and i think you
were kind of getting at that the
beginning too of is governance and data
democratization at odds like can you
have them both and it really comes down
a lot of times to what the policies are
that you create
and
a lot of folks for quite a long time
have gone with very traditional
role-based policies right if you are
this analyst working in this team you
get access if you are in hr you get this
kind of access
and i know uri is going to talk more
about this but what we found is that
these sorts of role-based access methods
of policy
enforcement have
like are sort of outdated and uri i
think you had more to mention with that
so a couple of things
first of all thinking about policies and
really policies or tools who say who can
do what
in what
and what jesse was alluding to earlier
is like
it's not only who can do what with what
but also in what context
because i may be a data analyst and i'm
spending
9 00 am till 1 pm
working for marketing in which case i'm
mailing a lot of customers our latest
shiny glossy catalog and with in which
case i need customers home addresses at
the second part of the day i the same me
looking at the same data but now the
context i'm operating on
is i need to understand
i don't know usage or invoices or
something completely different
that means i should not probably access
customers home addresses that data
should not be used as a
source product for everything downstream
from whatever reports i'm generating so
context is also important not just my
role but
just to pause for a moment and
acknowledge the fact that policies are
much more than just
access control
policies
talk about life cycle like we talked
about for example ingesting everything
dropping everything in sort of like a
holding place that's the beginning of a
life cycle it's first held then maybe
curated analyzed added quality to like
you test the high quality data that
there are no like broken records there
are no missing elements there are no
typos so you test that
then you
maybe
want to retain certain data for certain
durations maybe you want to
delete certain data like my credit card
example
maybe you are allowed to use certain
data for certain use cases and we are
not allowed to use certain data for
other use cases as i explained
so all of these are like worldly term
policies but it's all about what you
want to do with the data and in what
context
do you have any example where maybe the
sort of role-based classification where
you're allowed to access this depending
on your job function may not be
sufficient to
have a place where you're able to
extract the most out of the underlying
data
yeah we do there was a company that we
had spoken to that you know is a large
retailer
and
they were talking about how role-based
policies aren't necessarily working for
them very well anymore and it was you
know very close to what uri was uh
discussing just a few minutes ago
of you know they have analysts who are
working on you know sending out catalogs
or things like that right but let's say
that you also have access to you know
customers emails and things like that or
shipping addresses because you've had to
ship something to them so let's say they
bought i don't know a chair or something
and you have you know you're an analyst
you have access to their address and
whatnot because you had to send them the
chair
and now you see that oh our slip covers
for these chairs are on sale
well you know now you have a different
hat on you know now the analyst has a
marketing hat on right my focus right
now is marketing of sending out you know
marketing material emails on sales and
whatnot well if i collected that
customer's data for the purpose of just
shipping something that they had bought
i can't unless they've given permission
i can't use that same email address or
you know home address to send marketing
material to
now if your policy was just here's my
analysts who are working on you know
shipping data and then my marketing
analyst if i just had role-based access
control that would be fine these things
would not intersect but if you have the
same analyst who as uri had mentioned is
accessing these data sets same data sets
same you know engineer same analyst but
for completely different purposes some
of those are okay and some of those are
not and so really having these you know
they were one of the first companies
that we had talked to that were really
saying i need something more that is
more along a use case
like a purpose for what what am i using
that data for it's not just who am i and
what's my job but what am i going to be
using it for and in that context is it
acceptable to be accessing and using the
data that's a great example of things
now
when you're ingesting data maybe you're
getting these orders or maybe you are
looking at analytical stuff about where
this user is accessing from etc how do
you enforce the policies that you may
have already defined on data that's
coming in from all of these sources
you know things like you might have
streaming data you might have data
address transactional stuff so how do
you manage the policies or enforcing the
policies on incoming data especially
things that are fresh and new
so i love this question and i want to
add a little bit to it so i want to give
some background before we kind of jump
into that so
you know
when we're thinking about policies we're
often thinking about that step of
enforcing it right and i think what gets
lost is that there's really
two steps that happen before that and
there's there's probably more i'm
glossing over it all but there's
defining the policy
so you know do i get this from uh legal
is there some new law like you know ccpa
or gdpr or hipaa or something and you
know this is kind of where i'm getting
sort of the nuts and bolts of the policy
from defining it and then you know you
have to have someone who's implementing
it and so this is kind of what you're
talking about of you know kind of
getting into is it you know data at rest
is it an ingestion where am i writing
these policies and then there's
enforcing the policy which isn't just a
tool doing that but can also be
okay i'm going to you know scan through
and see how many people are accessing
this data set that i know really
shouldn't be accessed much at all
and the reason why i'm discussing these
distinct different pieces of you know
policy definition implementation and
enforcement is those can often be
different people and so having a line of
communication or something between those
folks uri and i have heard from many
companies
gets super lost and this can completely
break down so really acknowledging that
there's kind of these distinct parts of
it that you know and parts that have to
happen before enforcement even happens
is sort of an important thing to kind of
wrap your head around but uri can
definitely talk more about the like you
know actually getting in there and
enforcing
the policies
i agree with everything that was said
again yes sometimes for some reason the
people who actually audit the data or
actually not the data who audits the
data policies get sort of like forgotten
and it they're kind of important people
when we talked about why data governance
is important we said forget legal form
moment why data governance is important
because you want to make sure
the highest quality data gets to the
right people great who can prove that
it's the person who's monitoring the
policies who can prove that also that
person may be useful when you're talking
with the european commission and you
want to prove to them that you're
complying with gdpr so that's an
important person but talking about
enforcing policies on data as it comes
in so couple of thoughts though first of
all you have what we in google call
organization policies or org policies
those are like
what process can create what data store
well and this is kind of important even
before you have the data because you
don't want necessarily your apps in
europe to be beaming data to the us
maybe again you don't know what the data
is you don't know what it contains it
hasn't arrived yet but maybe you don't
even want to create a sync for it in a
region of the world where it shouldn't
be like because you are compliant with
gdpr because you promised your german
company that you work with that employee
information remains in germany that's
very common it's beyond gdpr maybe you
want to create a data store that is read
only or write once read only more
correctly because you are a financial
institution
and you are required by laws that
predate gdpr by a decade to hold
transaction information for fraud
detection and apparently there's fairly
detailed regulations about that
after that it's a bit of workflow
management the data has already landed
now you can say okay maybe i want to
build the teal system like we discussed
earlier where there's a landing zone
very few people can access this landing
zone maybe only machines can access the
landing zone and they do basic scraping
and augmenting and enriching and it
transfers to very few people very few
human people
and then later it's published to the
entire organization and maybe there's an
even later step where it's shared with
partners peers and consumers
and
this is by the way a pattern this
landing zone
intermediate zone public zone or
published zone this is a pattern we are
seeing more and more across the data
landscape in our data products and in
google we actually created a product for
that called dataplex which is first of a
kind which gives a first-class entity to
those kind of like holding zones
yeah what about
smaller to
medium-sized companies that might have
very basic data access policies are
there things that they can do today to
have this policy enforcement or applying
a policy when you don't have all of
these lines of communication established
let's say between legal to marketing to
pr to your engineers who are trying to
build something or analytics trying to
give feedback back into the business so
in a smaller context when you're not
necessarily dealing with a vast amount
of data maybe you have two data sources
or something what can they do with
limited amount of resources to improve
their state of data governance yeah
that's a really great question and it's
sort of one of these things that
can sometimes make it easier right so if
you have a bit less data and if your
organization is quite a bit smaller for
example erie and i had spoken with a
company that i think had
seven people total on their data
analytics team total in the entire
company it makes it a lot simpler you
know do they all get access or maybe
it's just steve because steve works with
all the scary stuff and so you know he
is the one or maybe it's jane that gets
it all so we've definitely seen the
ability for smaller companies with less
people and less data to be
maybe a bit more creative or not have as
much of a weight
but that isn't necessarily always the
case because there can also be small
organizations that do deal with a large
amount of data and to your point it can
be
challenging and i think uri has more to
add to this but one thing i will say is
that kind of as we had spoken in the
beginning of really selecting what is it
then that you need to govern and
especially if you don't have the head
count which so many folks don't you're
going to have to strategically think
about
where can i start you can't boil the
ocean but where can you start and maybe
it's five things maybe it's ten things
right maybe it's the things that hit
most the bottom line of the business or
that you know are the most scary because
as uri said that you know the auditor is
going to come in we've got to make sure
that this is is locked down i got to
make sure i can prove that this is
locked down so starting there but to not
get overwhelmed by all of it but to say
you know what if i just start somewhere
then i can build out but just something
yeah adding to what jesse said the case
of the small company with the small
amount of data is potentially simpler
it's actually quite common to have a
small company with a lot of data and
that is because maybe that company was
acquired or was acquiring that happens
and also maybe because it's so easy to
form a single simple mobile app to
generate
so much data especially if the app is
popular which is the good case it's a
good problem to have
now you are suddenly crossing the
threshold where regulators are starting
to notice you maybe your spend on cloud
storage is beginning to be painful to
your wallet
and you are still the same tiny team
this is only steve and steve is the only
one who understands this data what does
steve do
and the answer is
it's a little bit of what jesse said of
like start where you have the most
impact identify the 20 top 20 of the
data mostly used but also
there's a lot of built-in tools that
allow you to get immediate value without
a lot of investment google's cloud data
catalog
like out of the box it will give you a
search bar that allows you to search
across table name column names and file
names and maybe that makes a difference
again imagine just finding all the
tables that have email as a custom as a
column name
that is immediately useful can be
immediately impactful today and that
requires no installation it requires no
you know
investment in processing or compute it's
just there already similarly for amazon
there's something similar
for microsoft cloud or something similar
now that you have sort of like lowered
the watermark of pressure a little bit
down you can start thinking okay maybe i
want to consolidate data stores maybe i
want to consolidate data catalogs maybe
i want to go and shop for a third party
solution but start small identify the
top 20 impact and you will go from there
yeah i think that's such a great point
about starting with that 20
you know i had gone to a data governance
conference you know a couple years ago
now right
back when conferences were being held in
person
and there was this presentation about
kind of the ideal data governance state
right and there were these beautiful
images of you have this person doing
this thing and then these people and you
know all like this this perfect way that
it would all work and this score guy
stood up and he said
so i don't have the head count or the
budget to do any of that so how do i
do this
and the guy's response was well then you
just need to get it
and we sincerely hope that through you
know talking on podcasts and through the
book that folks will not feel like that
that they won't feel like well my only
recourse
is to hire 20 more people to get a
million well probably not even a million
i don't know 10 million or whatever
budget buy all the tools all the fancy
things and that's the only way that i
can do this and that's not the case uri
said you know kind of starting with
steve and and the 20 that steve can do
and then building from there i mean of
course clearly we feel very passionate
about this so we could talk for hours
and hours but if the folks listening
take nothing else away i hope that
that's one of the takeaways of this can
be condensed it can be made smaller and
then you can blow it out and make it
bigger
as you can yeah i think that's a great
suggestion or a great recommendation
right because even as a consumer for
example i'm better off knowing that
maybe if i'm using your app you have
some sort of governance policy in place
even though you might not be too big
maybe you don't have the headcount to
have this crazy structure around it but
you have some start i think that's
actually really nice uri you mentioned
earlier about one of the access policies
can be something like write ones read
many times etc for financial
transactions for example and makes me
wonder how do you keep track of the
source of data how do you track the
lineage of data is that important
why is it important so so let's start
from the actual end of the question
which is why is that important
so
couple of reasons one is
lineage provides a real important and
sometimes actionable context to the data
it's a very different kind of data if it
was sourced from a consumer contact
details table
then if it was sourced from the employee
database those are different kinds of
groups of people they have different
kinds of needs and requirements and
actually the data is shaped differently
for employees it's all about a user id
at
company.com for example that's a
different shape of email than for a
consumer
but the data itself will have the same
sort of like container it will be a
table of people with names maybe
addresses maybe phone numbers maybe
emails so that's an easy example where
context is important but
adding to that a little bit more let's
say you have data which is sensitive you
want all the derivatives of this data to
be sensitive as well and that's a
decision you can make automatically
there's no need for a human to come in
and check boxes you know that some point
upstream in the lineage graph this
column table whatever was deemed to be
sensitive just make sure that context
retains itself as long as the data is
evolving that is another how do you
collect lineage and how do you deal with
unknown data sources so
for lineage collection you really need
the tool the the speed of evolution of
data in today's environment really
requires you to have some sort of
automated tooling that as data is
created the information about where it
came from physically like this file
bucket that data set is recorded that's
like humans cannot really effectively do
that because they will make mistakes or
they'll just be lazy i'm lazy i know
that
what do you do with unknown data sources
so this is where good defaults are
really important there's a data somebody
some random person who is not available
for questions at the moment has created
the data source and this is being used
widely now you don't know what the data
source is so you don't know quality you
don't know sensitivity and you need to
do something about it because tomorrow
the regulator is coming for a visit
so good defaults means like what's your
risk profile and if your risk profile is
this is going to come up in the
view or did
just mark it as sensitive and put it on
somebody's task list to go into it later
and try and figure out what this is if
you have a good lineage collection tool
then
you will be able to track all the
byproducts and be able to automatically
categorize them does that make sense
yeah absolutely i think maybe applying
the strongest most restrictive one for
derived data is
maybe the safest approach right and that
totally makes sense
can you we've talked a lot about just
regulatory
requirements right we've mentioned it
can you maybe give some examples of what
regulatory requirements are out there we
mentioned gdpr ccpa hepa previously so
maybe can you just dig into one of those
or maybe all of those briefly just say
what exists right now and what are some
of those most popular regulatory
requirements that you really have to
think about so
first of all disclaimer not a lawyer not
an expert on regulations and also this
is important regulations are different
depending not only on where you are and
what language you speak but also on what
kind of data you collect and what do you
use it for everybody is concerned about
gdpr and ccpa so i'll talk about them
but i'll also talk about what exists
beyond that scope
gdpr general data protection
and ccpa which is the california
consumer access protection really
novel a little bit
in that they say oh
if you are collecting
people's data you should pay attention
to that now this is not going to be an
analysis of gdpr and whether it's apply
to that talk to your lawyers
but in broad strokes what they mean is
if you collect
people's data you should do two very
simple things first of all let those
people know that sounds surprising but
people did not used to do that and there
were unexpected things that happened as
a result for that
second of all if you are collecting
people's data give them a the option to
open out like i don't want my data to be
collection that may mean i cannot
i cannot require the service from you
but i have the option to say no
and
again not many people understand that
but at least they have the option they
also have the option to come back later
and say hey you know what i want to be
taken off your system i love google it's
a great company i enjoyed my gmail very
much but i've changed my mind i'm moving
over to a competitor please delete
everything you know about me so i can
rest more easily and that's another
option
both gdpr and ccp are also novel in the
fact that they contain teeth
which means there's a financial penalty
if people fail to comply people meaning
companies fail to comply and there's a
whole lot of other like gdpr is a robust
piece of legislation it has hundreds of
pages
but there's also care to be taken as a
thread across the the regulation around
please be mindful about which
companies services vendors people
process people's data
it will be highly remiss if we did not
mention two classes of regulation beyond
gdpr and ccpa those are
health related regulations in the us
there's hepa there's an equivalent in
europe there's equivalents actually all
across the planet and those are like
what do you do with medical data like
do i really want
people that are not my own personal
physician to know that i have a certain
medical condition what do you do about
that if my data is to be used in the
creation of life-saving drug
how is that to be used and we were
hearing a lot about that in
unfortunately the pandemic like people
were developing drugs very rapidly and
we were hearing a lot about that there's
another class of regulation
which governs financial transactions
again highly sensitive because i don't
want people to know
how much money i have i won't want
people to know who i negotiate and do
business with but sometimes
banks need to know that because certain
patterns of your transactions indicate
fault and that's a
valuable service they can provide for
detection for the preventions there's
also bad actors we have this situation
in eastern europe banks
russian banks are being blocked there's
a way for banks to detect
trading with those entities and block
them and again russian banks are a
recent example but there are more older
examples of unwanted actors and
you can insert your financial crime here
so that will be my my answer yeah thanks
for that like quick walk through of
those that it's really i think going
back to what you were emphasizing
earlier about starting somewhere with
respect to data governance you know it's
all the more important when you have all
of these policies and regulatory
requirements really to at least be aware
of what you should be doing with data or
what your responsibilities are as a
company or as an engineer or whoever you
are listening to the podcast
i want to ask another thing is about
just data storage i think there are
specifically there are countries or
there are places where they say data
residency rules apply where you can't
really move data out of the country can
you give an example about how
that impacts
your business how does that impact your
maybe operations where you deploy your
business etc
a general again not a lawyer but
generally speaking keep data in the same
geographic region where it was sourced
for is usually a good practice
that begets a lot of like interesting
questions which do not have a straight
answer do not have a simple answer like
okay i'm keeping old let's say i have
let's take something simple i have a
music app the music app makes money by
sending targeted ads to people listening
to music fairly simple now in order to
send targeted ads i need to collect data
about the people listening to music for
example what music they are listening to
fairly simple so far now
where do you store that data okay so all
we said in the podcast store it in the
region of the world it was collected
from great
now here's a question where do you store
the information about the existence of
this data in the country basically if
you have now a search bar to search for
music listened by people in germany
does this search
like do you need to go into each
individual region where you store data
and search for that data or is there a
centralized search
as things stand right now
the regulation on metadata which is what
i'm talking about the existence of data
about data does not exist yet it's
trending to be also restricted by region
and that
presents all kinds of interesting
challenges the good news is
if you have this problem that means that
your music application was hugely
successful adopted all over the planet
and you have users all over the planet
that probably means you're in a good
place so that's a happy start
yeah
i think also when you look at machine
learning ai being so prevalent right now
in the industry i have to ask when you
are trying to build a model out of data
that is local to a region maybe or maybe
it contains personally identifiable
information and the user comes in and
says hey i want to be forgotten how do
you deal with this sort of derived data
that exists in the form of an ai
application or just a machine learning
model where maybe you can't get back the
data that you started with but you have
used it in your training data or test
data or something like that that's a
really good question and you know to
kind of even go back before we're even
talking about ml and ai
you know it's really
funny well i don't know if it's funny
but you know you can't go in
and forget somebody unless you have a
way to find that person right
so one of the things that we found in
kind of interviewing companies kind of
as they're really trying to get their
governance off the ground and be in
compliance is they can't find people to
forget them they can't find that data
and this is why it's so important you
know i can't extract that data i can't
delete it if you've ever had the case of
where you've unsubscribed from something
and you don't get emails for a while
only to then all of a sudden you get
emails again and you're wondering why
that is well it's because the governance
wasn't that great right and i don't mean
governance in terms of like security and
not that it's any malicious point on
those folks at all right but it shows
you
of exactly what you're saying of where
is that kind of streaming down and uri
was making this point of really looking
at the lineage of kind of finding where
are all the places where this is going
and now you can't capture all these
things but the better governance that
you have and
as you're thinking about you know how do
i prioritize right like we were kind of
talking about there might be some i need
to make data-driven decisions in the
business so these are some you know
things that i'm going to prioritize in
terms of my classifying my lineage
tracking and then maybe there's other
things related to regulations of i have
to prove this to that poor auditor that
has to go in and look at things so maybe
i prioritize some of those things so i
think even before we get in to you know
machine learning and things like that
these should be some of the things that
folks are thinking about to like put
eyes on and why some of that governance
and strategy that you put into place
beforehand is so important but
specifically with the ml and ai uri
that's definitely more up your alley
than mine yeah i can talk about that
briefly so first of all as jesse
mentioned the fact that you don't have
good data governance and people are
trying to unsubscribe and you don't know
who these people are and you're doing
your best but that's not good enough
that's not good enough and if somebody
has a stick to beat you with they will
wave that stick
so besides that here's something that
has worked well for google actually
which is
when you're training ai model again it's
highly tempting to use all of the
features you can including people's data
and all that there's sometimes very good
results that you can achieve without
actually saving any data
about people and there's two examples
for that one is if anybody who's
listening to this is familiar with the
covid exposures notification app that's
an app and it's widely documented and
just look up for it in other apples or
google's information pages that app does
not contain anything about you and does
not share anything about you the tldr on
how it works it's a rolling random
identifier that's keeping a rolling
random identifier of everything you
everybody you have met
and if one of those rolling random
identifiers happens to have a positive
diagnosis then it's that the other
people know but nothing personal is
actually kept no location no usernames
no phone numbers nothing just a rolling
random identifier which by itself does
not mean anything that's one example the
other example is actually very cool it's
called federated learning it's a whole
recognized technique which is the basis
for autocomplete in mobile phone
keyboards so if you type on your mobile
phone both apple and google you will see
a couple of suggestions for words and
you can actually build whole sentences
out of that without typing a single
letter and that is kind of fun
the way this works is there's a machine
learning model that's trying to predict
what word you're going to use and it
predicts that by looking at the sentence
that machine learning model runs locally
on your phone
the only data is shared is actually okay
i've spent a day predicting words and
during this day apparently sunshine was
more common than rainfall so i'm going
to
beam to
the centralized database
sunshine is more common than rainfall
there's nothing about the user though
there's nothing about the individual but
it's useful information and apparently
it works
so how do you deal with machine learning
models try first not to save any data at
all
yes there are some cases where you have
to which
again not being a huge expert of it but
in some cases you will need to rebuild
and retrain your machine learning model
try to make those cases the exception
not the rule yeah i really like your
first example of code right where you
can achieve the same result by using pii
and also without using pii it just
requires you to think about a way to
achieve the same goals without putting
all of the personal information in that
path and i think that's a great example
i want to switch gears a little bit into
just the monitoring aspects of it you
have like regulatory requirements maybe
for monitoring or maybe just as a
company you want to know that the ideal
policies access controls that you have
are not being violated what are
strategies for monitoring do you have
any examples
that is a great question and i'm sure
anyone who's listening who has dealt
with this problem is like yes
how do you do that
because it's
really really challenging if i had a
dollar even a penny for every time i
talk to a company and they ask me but is
there a dashboard like is there a
dashboard where i can see everything
that's going on
so
to your point it's definitely a big it's
an issue it's a problem of being able to
do that there certainly are some tools
that are coming out that are
aiming to be better at that certainly
uri can speak more on that dataplex is a
product that he mentioned and some of
the monitoring capabilities in there are
directly from
years of you know interviews that we did
with customers and
companies of what they needed to see to
enable them to better know what the heck
is going on with my data estate how is
it doing who's accessing what how many
violations are there
so
i suppose my my answer to your question
is there
there's no great way to do it quite yet
and
you know save for some tooling that can
help you i think it's another place of
defining
i can't monitor everything what do i
have to monitor
most what do i have to make sure that
i'm monitoring and how do i start there
and then branch out and i think another
important part is really defining who is
going to do what that's one thing that
we found a lot is that if it's not
someone's job someone's explicit job
it's often not going to get done so
really saying okay steve poor steve
steve has got so much steve you need to
monitor how many folks are accessing
this particular
zone within our data lake that has all
of the you know sensitive stuff or what
have you
but defining kind of those tasks and who
is going to do them is definitely a
start but i know uri has more on this
yeah just briefly it's a common customer
problem and customers are like i
understand that the file storage product
has a detailed dock i understand how the
data analytics product has a detailed
log everything has a detailed log but i
want a single log to look at which shows
me both and that's why we built dataplex
which is sort of like a unifying
management console that doesn't care
where your data is it tells you how your
data is governed who's accessing it
what interface they're doing and whether
and it's a first it was launched
recently
and it's intended not to be a new way of
processing your data but actually
approaching at how customers think about
the data customers don't think about
their data in terms of files and tables
customers thinks about their data as
this is customer data this is
pre-processed data this is data that i
am willing to share and we are trying to
approach those metaphors with our
products rather than giving them a most
excellent file storage which is only the
basis of the use case we also give the
most excellent file storage
yeah i think a lot of tools are
certainly adding in that sort of
monitoring auditing capabilities that i
usually see with your products and
that's actually a great step in the
right direction
i want to start wrapping things up and i
think this sort of culture of having
some governance in place or just
starting somewhere is really great and
when i look at say a large company they
usually have different kinds of
trainings that you have to take that
explicitly spell out
what is okay to do in this company what
can you access there are security-based
controls for accessing sensitive
information audits and all of that but
if you take that same thing in an
unregulated industry maybe or a small to
medium-sized company how do you build
that sort of data culture how do you
train your people who are coming in and
joining your company about what your
data philosophy or principles are or
data governance policies are do you have
any examples or do you have any takes on
how someone can get started on some of
those aspects it's a really good
question and something
that often gets overlooked like you said
in a big company there's okay we know we
have to have trainings and things like
this but in in smaller companies or
unregulated industries it often gets
forgotten and i think you hit on an
important point of having some of those
principles again it's a place of
starting somewhere but i think even more
than that it's just being purposeful
we literally have an entire chapter in
the book dedicated to
culture because that's how important we
feel it is and i feel like it's one of
those places of where
the people really matter right we've
talked so much in this last hour plus
together of there's these tools
ingestion storage done or not you know
and a little bit about the people but
that's really where the culture can come
into play and it's about being planful
and it doesn't have to be fancy it
doesn't have to be fancy trainings and
whatnot but as you had mentioned you
know having
principles that you say okay this is how
we're going to use data this is what
we're going to do
and taking the time to get the folks who
are going to be touching the data at
least on board with that
and i had mentioned it before but really
defining roles and responsibilities and
who does what there can't be one person
that does everything it has to be sort
of a spreading out of responsibilities
but again you have to be planful of
thinking what are those tasks it doesn't
have to be 100 tasks but what are these
tasks let's literally list them out okay
now who's going to do what because
unless we define that you know
joe is going to get stuck doing all the
curation and he's going to quit and
that's just not going to work
so adding to that a little bit it's not
just again small company unregulated
industry there's not a huge hammer
waiting for them how do they get data
governance and
being planful is a huge part of that
it's also about like i've already
confessed to being lazy so i have no
issue confessing to it again someday you
will believe me but it's telling the
employees what's in it for them and data
governance is not a gatekeeper it's a
huge enabler do you want to quickly find
the data that's relevant to you to order
to do the next version of the music app
oh
then you better when you create a new
data source just add those like five
words saying what is this new database
about who was it sourced from does it
contain pi just click those five check
boxes
and
in return we'll give you a better index
oh you want to make sure that you don't
need to go in requisition all the time
new permissions for data make sure you
don't save pii oh you don't know what
pii is here's a handy classifier just
make sure you run it as part of your
workflow we will take it from there and
again that is the first step in making
data work for you other than poor joe
who's nobody is classifying in the
organization so everybody like leans on
him and he quits other than doing that
show employees what's in it for them
they will be the ones to classify that's
actually good news because they're
actually the ones who know what the data
is joe has no idea
and that will be a happier organization
yeah i think that's a really nice note
to end it on that you know you don't
really need to look at this as a
regulatory requirement alone but really
look at it as what can these solid
governance policies do for you what can
it enable in the future what can it
simplify for you i think that's
fantastic
with that i'd like to end jesse and uri
thank you so much for coming on the show
i'm going to leave a link to the book in
our show notes
thank you again this is akshay munchale
for software engineering radio thank you
for listening and the book is data
governance the definitive guide the
product is cloud dataplex and they are
both googleable
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at
se-radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening